Clarke, James Freeman, 1810-1888. James Freeman Clarke additional papers, 1717-1889 (MS Am 1569.1): Guide.
James Freeman Clarke additional papers,
1717-1889.
Houghton Library, Harvard College Library, Harvard University
MS Am 1569.1
Clarke, James Freeman, 1810-1888.
5.5 linear feet (5 boxes)
Sermons, compositions, journals, and student papers of the Unitarian clergyman and author James Freeman Clarke. Also includes some family papers.
58M-223, 58M-224, and 58M-225. Deposited by James Freeman Clarke; gift, 1956-1967.
There are no restrictions on physical access to this material.
James Freeman Clarke was a Unitarian clergyman, author, and reformer closely associated with the New England Transcendentalists. He was the son of Samuel C. Clarke and Rebecca Parker Hull Clarke. James was essentially raised by his step-grandfather, James Freeman (1759-1835). He received an AB from Harvard College in 1829 and a degree from the Harvard Divinity School in 1833. He was minister in Louisville, Kentucky (1833-1840) and at the Church of the Disciples in Boston (1841-1850, 1854-1888). Clarke was editor of the Western Messenger (1836-1839). In 1839 he married Anna Huidekoper Clarke (1814-1897), the daughter of Harm Jan Huidekoper, businessman, lay theologian, and founder of Meadville Theological Seminary.
Arranged into the following series:
I. Sermons of James Freeman Clarke
II. Sermons of James Freeman
III. Compositions and other papers of James Freeman Clarke
IV. Scrapbooks, journals, sketchbooks, financial records and other papers of James Freeman Clarke
V. Family papers
[NOTE: During the 2015 recataloging, the order of materials was retained in roughly former call-number order].
Includes autograph manuscript sermons preached by James Freeman Clarke in Louisville and elsewhere, papers from his student days at Harvard College, poems, short stories, sketches of Europe and New England, journals, scrapbooks, a commonplace book, etchings of Clarke, and other material.
Family papers include: autograph manuscript sermons by his step-grandfather James Freeman; diaries of his daughter Lillian Freeman Clarke; a scrapbook of photographs of his daughter Cora Huidekoper Clarke; various family letters mounted in a scrapbook regarding family news and financial matters; a Timothy Fuller letter book; and other items.
See HOLLIS and OASIS for more J F Clarke material held by the Houghton Library and other repositories at Harvard.
- I. Sermons of James Freeman Clarke
  58M-223. Formerly MS Am 1569.1 (no item numbers).
  - Clarke, James Freeman, 1810-1888. Sermons written and preached in Louisville and later: autograph manuscript, 1833-1860.
    Autograph manuscript sermons.
    Dates listed below are written on the sermons and indicate dates each was delivered.
    Item (1) includes a manuscript note: "written & preached 1833-1840 in Louisville but many repreached 1840-1859."
    Includes the following items:
    - Clarke, James Freeman, 1810-1888. Acts 3: 26.: autograph manuscript sermon, 1840-1843., (1); 1 folders
      Includes a manuscript note found with sermons series: "Written & preached 1833-1840 in Louisville but many repreached 1840-1859."
    - Clarke, James Freeman, 1810-1888. Acts VII: 26.: autograph manuscript sermon, 1837-1838., (2); 1 folders
    - Clarke, James Freeman, 1810-1888. Acts X: 15, 28: autograph manuscript sermon, 1835-1845., (3); 1 folders
    - Clarke, James Freeman, 1810-1888. Acts XX: 35: autograph manuscript sermon, 1837-1841., (4); 1 folders
    - Clarke, James Freeman, 1810-1888. I Corinthians X: 1-11: autograph manuscript sermon, 1839., (5); 1 folders
    - Clarke, James Freeman, 1810-1888. I Corinthians XII: 12: autograph manuscript sermon, 1835-1838., (6); 1 folders
    - Clarke, James Freeman, 1810-1888. 2 Corinthians III: 18: autograph manuscript sermon, 1834., (7); 1 folders
    - Clarke, James Freeman, 1810-1888. 2 Corinthians IV: 18: autograph manuscript sermon, 1836-1860., (8); 1 folders
    - Clarke, James Freeman, 1810-1888. Deuteronomy X: 15, 21, 22: autograph manuscript sermon, 1836-1841., (9); 1 folders
    - Clarke, James Freeman, 1810-1888. Ecclesiastes IX: 10: autograph manuscript sermon, 1833 and undated., (10); 1 folders
      2 sermons.
    - Clarke, James Freeman, 1810-1888. Ecclesiastes XII: 1: autograph manuscript sermon, 1833-1834., (11); 1 folders
    - Clarke, James Freeman, 1810-1888. Galatians II: 16: autograph manuscript sermon, 1837-1839., (12); 1 folders
    - Clarke, James Freeman, 1810-1888. Genesis II: 18: autograph manuscript sermon, 1836-1837., (13); 1 folders
    - Clarke, James Freeman, 1810-1888. Habakkuk III: 2: autograph manuscript sermon, 1834-1837., (14); 1 folders
    - Clarke, James Freeman, 1810-1888. Hebrews II: 15: autograph manuscript sermon, undated., (15); 1 folders
    - Clarke, James Freeman, 1810-1888. Hebrews XI: 4: autograph manuscript sermon, 1838-1843., (16); 1 folders
    - Clarke, James Freeman, 1810-1888. Isaiah XXXV: 8: autograph manuscript sermon, 1837., (17); 1 folders
    - Clarke, James Freeman, 1810-1888. Isaiah XXXVIII: 1: autograph manuscript sermon, 1838-1842., (18); 1 folders
    - Clarke, James Freeman, 1810-1888. Jeremiah XIII: 23: autograph manuscript sermon, 1834-1835., (19); 1 folders
    - Clarke, James Freeman, 1810-1888. John II: 1-12: autograph manuscript sermon, 1839., (20); 1 folders
    - Clarke, James Freeman, 1810-1888. John III: 7: autograph manuscript sermon, 1834-1840., (21); 1 folders
    - Clarke, James Freeman, 1810-1888. John VI: 63: autograph manuscript sermon, 1836., (22); 1 folders
    - Clarke, James Freeman, 1810-1888. John VIII: 32-34: autograph manuscript sermon, 1834-1838., (23); 1 folders
    - Clarke, James Freeman, 1810-1888. John XII: 50: autograph manuscript sermon, 1840., (24); 1 folders
    - Clarke, James Freeman, 1810-1888. John XV: 15: autograph manuscript sermon, undated., (25); 1 folders
    - Clarke, James Freeman, 1810-1888. John XVIII: 38: autograph manuscript sermon, 1834-1837., (26); 1 folders
    - Clarke, James Freeman, 1810-1888. I John I: 8-9: autograph manuscript sermon, 1835-1837., (27); 1 folders
    - Clarke, James Freeman, 1810-1888. Luke X: 38-42: autograph manuscript sermon, 1837., (28); 1 folders
    - Clarke, James Freeman, 1810-1888. Luke X: 41-42: autograph manuscript sermon, undated., (29); 1 folders
    - Clarke, James Freeman, 1810-1888. Luke X: 42: autograph manuscript sermon, 1838-1839., (30); 1 folders
    - Clarke, James Freeman, 1810-1888. Luke XII: 50: autograph manuscript sermon, 1835., (31); 1 folders
    - Clarke, James Freeman, 1810-1888. Luke XXI: 13: autograph manuscript sermon, 1835-1836., (32); 1 folders
    - Clarke, James Freeman, 1810-1888. Luke XVII: 20-21: autograph manuscript sermon, 1836-1837., (33); 1 folders
    - Clarke, James Freeman, 1810-1888. Mark X: 21: autograph manuscript sermon, 1837-1839., (34); 1 folders
    - Clarke, James Freeman, 1810-1888. Mark XIV: 8: autograph manuscript sermon, 1838-1842., (35); 1 folders
    - Clarke, James Freeman, 1810-1888. Matthew III: 3: autograph manuscript sermon, 1838-1859., (36); 1 folders
    - Clarke, James Freeman, 1810-1888. Matthew V: 8: autograph manuscript sermon, 1837-1843., (37); 1 folders
    - Clarke, James Freeman, 1810-1888. Matthew V: 17: autograph manuscript sermon, 1833-1834., (38); 1 folders
    - Clarke, James Freeman, 1810-1888. Matthew VIII: 23-27: autograph manuscript sermon, 1839-1842., (39); 1 folders
    - Clarke, James Freeman, 1810-1888. Matthew XI: 11: autograph manuscript sermon, 1837-1844., (40); 1 folders
    - Clarke, James Freeman, 1810-1888. Matthew XI: 29: autograph manuscript sermon, 1834., (41); 1 folders
    - Clarke, James Freeman, 1810-1888. Matthew XII: 30: autograph manuscript sermon, undated., (42); 1 folders
    - Clarke, James Freeman, 1810-1888. Matthew XII: 46-50: autograph manuscript sermon, 1839., (43); 1 folders
    - Clarke, James Freeman, 1810-1888. Matthew XIII: 54: autograph manuscript sermon, 1836-1837., (44); 1 folders
    - Clarke, James Freeman, 1810-1888. Matthew XVI: 6: autograph manuscript sermon, 1839., (45); 1 folders
    - Clarke, James Freeman, 1810-1888. Matthew XXIII: 29-31: autograph manuscript sermon, 1838-1852., (46); 1 folders
    - Clarke, James Freeman, 1810-1888. Matthew XXV: 27: autograph manuscript sermon, 1837., (47); 1 folders
    - Clarke, James Freeman, 1810-1888. Matthew XXV: 31, 46: autograph manuscript sermon, 1837-1839., (48); 1 folders
    - Clarke, James Freeman, 1810-1888. Matthew XXVI: 41: autograph manuscript sermon, 1839-1842., (49); 1 folders
    - Clarke, James Freeman, 1810-1888. Matthew XXVI: 47: autograph manuscript sermon, 1833-1844., (50); 1 folders
    - Clarke, James Freeman, 1810-1888. Numbers XXIII: 10: autograph manuscript sermon, 1839-1840., (51); 1 folders
    - Clarke, James Freeman, 1810-1888. I Peter III: 19: autograph manuscript sermon, 1839-1841., (52); 1 folders
    - Clarke, James Freeman, 1810-1888. Philippians III: 13-14: autograph manuscript sermon, 1839-1841., (53); 1 folders
    - Clarke, James Freeman, 1810-1888. Psalm XIX: 1: autograph manuscript sermon, 1834-1837., (54); 1 folders
    - Clarke, James Freeman, 1810-1888. Psalm XC: 12: autograph manuscript sermon, 1834-1843., (55); 1 folders
    - Clarke, James Freeman, 1810-1888. Psalm CXXXVI: 1-6: autograph manuscript sermon, undated., (56); 1 folders
    - Clarke, James Freeman, 1810-1888. Romans XIII: 11: autograph manuscript sermon, 1836-1839., (57); 1 folders
    - Clarke, James Freeman, 1810-1888. Song of Solomon II: 11-12: autograph manuscript sermon, 1838-1839., (58); 1 folders
    - Clarke, James Freeman, 1810-1888. I Thessalonians IV: 13: autograph manuscript sermon, 1838-1840., (59); 1 folders
    - Clarke, James Freeman, 1810-1888. Zechariah IV: 10: autograph manuscript sermon, 1838-1852., (60); 1 folders
    - Clarke, James Freeman, 1810-1888. Various compositions: autograph manuscript, undated., (60a); 1 folders
      Loose materials found within sermons.
- II. Sermons of James Freeman
  - Freeman, James, 1759-1835. Sermons: autograph manuscript, 1783-1825.
    Arranged in 2 groups, first by sermon number, then alphabetically.
    Item (61) includes a manuscript note: "All, or nearly all, [of] these sermons were published as Sermons and charges by James Freeman, Boston, 1832. The MSS copies are valuable for showing when and how often these sermons were delivered."
    - Freeman, James, 1759-1835. Table of contents: autograph manuscript, undated., (61); 1 folders
    - Freeman, James, 1759-1835. Sermon I: autograph manuscript sermon, 1788-?, (62); 1 folders
      Incomplete.
    - Freeman, James, 1759-1835. Sermon IV: autograph manuscript sermon, undated., (63); 1 folders
    - Freeman, James, 1759-1835. Sermon V: autograph manuscript sermon, undated., (64); 1 folders
    - Freeman, James, 1759-1835. Sermon VIII: autograph manuscript sermon, 1816-1825., (65); 1 folders
    - Freeman, James, 1759-1835. Sermon IX: autograph manuscript sermon, undated., (66); 1 folders
    - Freeman, James, 1759-1835. Sermon X: autograph manuscript sermon, undated., (66a); 1 folders
    - Freeman, James, 1759-1835. Sermon XI: autograph manuscript sermon, 1789-1822 and undated., (67); 1 folders
      2 versions.
    - Freeman, James, 1759-1835. Sermon XII: autograph manuscript sermon, 1810-1824., (68); 1 folders
    - Freeman, James, 1759-1835. Sermon XIV: autograph manuscript sermon, 1794-1825., (69); 1 folders
    - Freeman, James, 1759-1835. Sermon XVII: autograph manuscript sermon, undated., (70); 1 folders
    - Freeman, James, 1759-1835. Sermon XVIII: autograph manuscript sermon, undated., (70a); 1 folders
    - Freeman, James, 1759-1835. Sermon XX: autograph manuscript sermon, 1783-1824., (71); 1 folders
    - Freeman, James, 1759-1835. Sermon XXI: autograph manuscript sermon, 1792-1820., (72); 1 folders
    - Freeman, James, 1759-1835. A charge: printed sermon with manuscript annotations, 1823., (73); 1 folders
    - Freeman, James, 1759-1835. Christmas: autograph manuscript sermons, 1801-1823., (74); 1 folders
      3 versions.
    - Freeman, James, 1759-1835. Do thyself no harm: autograph manuscript sermon, 1791-1823., (75); 1 folders
    - Freeman, James, 1759-1835. Duties resulting from ... minister: autograph manuscript sermon, 1809., (76); 1 folders
    - Freeman, James, 1759-1835. The end of the year: autograph manuscript sermons, 1806-1810., (77); 1 folders
    - Freeman, James, 1759-1835. Epiphany: autograph manuscript sermon, 1816., (78); 1 folders
    - Freeman, James, 1759-1835. Fast: autograph manuscript sermon, 1807-1824., (79); 1 folders
    - Freeman, James, 1759-1835. If sinners entice thee, consent thou not: autograph manuscript sermon, 1786-1825., (80); 1 folders
    - Freeman, James, 1759-1835. The light of the moon shall be as the light of the sun: autograph manuscript sermon, 1809-1815., (81); 1 folders
    - Freeman, James, 1759-1835. Long life a blessing: autograph manuscript sermon, 1810-1824., (82); 1 folders
    - Freeman, James, 1759-1835. Fragments of sermons: autograph manuscript sermons, various dates., (83); 1 folders
- III. Compositions and other papers of James Freeman Clarke
  58M-224. Formerly MS Am 1569.2 (1-14).
  Arrangement left as found in 2015 recataloging. Primarily in former call-number order.
  Includes compositions, letters, sketches, church papers, additional sermons, among other material.
  - Clarke, James Freeman, 1810-1888. The Independent voter, and Independent party in politics: autograph manuscript (unsigned) speech, 1884., (84); 6s.(7p.) in 1 folder.
    Given April 7, 1884 at dinner of Massachusetts Reform Club.
    Formerly MS Am 1569.2 (1).
  - Clarke, James Freeman, 1810-1888. Papers on lectures of campaign of 1884: autograph manuscript, 1884., (85); 1 folders
    Formerly MS Am 1569.2 (2).
  - Clarke, James Freeman, 1810-1888. European trip of 1882: visiting cards, drawings, 1882., (86); 1 folders
    Formerly MS Am 1569.2 (3).
  - Clarke, James Freeman, 1810-1888. European trip of 1882: England - letters of introduction, receipts, and visiting cards, etc., 1882., (87); 1 folders
  - Clarke, James Freeman, 1810-1888. European trip of 1882: Letters of introduction for England, outside of London, 1882., (88); 1 folders
  - Clarke, James Freeman, 1810-1888. European trip of 1882: Miscellaneous letters, 1882., (89); 1 folders
  - Clarke, James Freeman, 1810-1888. European trip of 1882: Tickets, visiting cards, letters, 1882., (90); 1 folders
  - Clarke, James Freeman, 1810-1888. European trip of 1882: Miscellaneous printed items, receipts, menus, letters, etc..., 1882., (91); 1 folders
  - Clarke, James Freeman, 1810-1888. Miscellaneous papers covering later years: photographs, undated., (92); 1 folders
    Includes cartes-de-visite (card photographs) and cabinet photographs of Clarke, the Clarke family, and William Ellery Channing.
    Formerly MS Am 1569.2 (4).
  - Clarke, James Freeman, 1810-1888. Miscellaneous papers covering later years: Notes, lists, letters, other miscellany, 1840-1888., (93); 1 folders
  - Clarke, James Freeman, 1810-1888. Invitations from churches and appointments to positions, various dates., (94); 2 folders
    Formerly MS Am 1569.2 (5).
  - Clarke, James Freeman, 1810-1888. Louisville accounts, various dates., (95); 1 folders
    Formerly MS Am 1569.2 (6).
  - Clarke, James Freeman, 1810-1888. Papers as student at Harvard College; 1825-1829., (96); 2 folders
    Formerly MS Am 1569.2 (7).
  - Clarke, James Freeman, 1810-1888. Journal of Understanding: manuscript, undated., (97); 9s.(18p.) in 1 folder.
    Formerly MS Am 1569.2 (8).
  - Clarke, James Freeman, 1810-1888. Journal of People and Things: manuscript, undated., (98); 2s.(4p.) in 1 folder.
    Formerly MS Am 1569.2 (9).
  - Clarke, James Freeman, 1810-1888. A temperance tale: autograph manuscript (signed, initials); no place, undated., (99); 2s.(5p.) in 1 folder.
    Formerly MS Am 1569.2 (10).
  - Clarke, James Freeman, 1810-1888. Loose poems for Exotics: autograph manuscript, printed, undated., (100); 1 folders
    Formerly MS Am 1569.2 (11).
  - Clarke, James Freeman, 1810-1888. Leaves omitted from the Biography: autograph manuscript, undated., (101); 1 folders
    Formerly MS Am 1569.2 (12).
  - Clarke, James Freeman, 1810-1888. Squash End. A Yankee Story: autograph manuscript (unsigned); no place, undated., (102); 39s.(39p.) in 1 folder.
    Formerly MS Am 1569.2 (13).
  - Clarke, James Freeman, 1810-1888. Miscellaneous papers: manuscript, printed, autograph manuscript, various dates., (103)
    Includes a drawing, notes on family, "Bowdoin dissertation", power of attorney for JFC, bank checks, and other papers.
    Formerly MS Am 1569.2 (13a).
  - Clarke, James Freeman, 1810-1888. Miscellaneous church papers: Sunday school record and Classes in their order: autograph manuscript, 1860-1862., (104); 1 volume in 1 folder.
    Formerly MS Am 1569.2 (14).
  - Clarke, James Freeman, 1810-1888. Miscellaneous church papers: Church of the Disciples lists: autograph manuscript, circa 1841-1876., (105); 1 volume in 1 folder.
  - Clarke, James Freeman, 1810-1888. Miscellaneous church papers: Pastoral notebook and Notes on the history of the reformation: autograph manuscript, 1866-1872., (106); 1 volume in 1 folder.
  - Clarke, James Freeman, 1810-1888. Miscellaneous church papers: Marriage certificates: printed documents with manuscript additions, circa 1845-1848., (107); 1 folders
  - Clarke, James Freeman, 1810-1888. Miscellaneous church papers: Loose notes: autograph manuscript, undated., (108); 1 folders
    Includes notes and also pages probably missing from sermons.
  - Clarke, James Freeman, 1810-1888. Miscellaneous church papers: Printed miscellany, various dates., (109); 1 folders
    Clippings and leaflets.
  - Clarke, James Freeman, 1810-1888. Miscellaneous church papers: Letters, various dates., (110); 1 folders
  - Greenwood, Mr. Miscellaneous church papers: Sermon at ordination of James Freeman Clarke: manuscript (in Sarah Clarke's hand), 1833., (111); 1 folders
  - Miscellaneous church papers: Obituary? of James Freeman Clarke: manuscript (heavily edited) essay, undated., (112); 1 folders
  - Clarke, James Freeman, 1810-1888. Miscellaneous church papers: Additional sermons and other writings: autograph manuscript, various dates.
    - Clarke, James Freeman, 1810-1888. After the death of Maria Bond: autograph manuscript sermon, 1872., (113); 1 folders
    - Clarke, James Freeman, 1810-1888. Agenda, work at home with amanuensis, etc...: autograph manuscript, 1885., (114); 1 folders
    - Clarke, James Freeman, 1810-1888. Character and work of William Greenleaf Eliot: autograph manuscript discourse, 1887., (115); 1 folders
    - Clarke, James Freeman, 1810-1888. Church of the Disciples memoranda: autograph manuscript, undated., (116); 1 folders
    - Clarke, James Freeman, 1810-1888. A house which grows: autograph manuscript sermon, 1880, (117); 1 folders
    - Clarke, James Freeman, 1810-1888. Dedication of the Church at Magnolia: autograph manuscript sermon, 1885 July 5., (118); 1 folders
    - Clarke, James Freeman, 1810-1888. Dedication of new church and Dedication of Church of the Disciple: autograph manuscript, 1869., (119); 1 folders
    - Clarke, James Freeman, 1810-1888. Dr. Bellows and the Broad Church: autograph manuscript, undated., (120); 1 folders
    - Clarke, James Freeman, 1810-1888. The fundamental idea of this church [first line]: autograph manuscript, undated., (121); 1 folders
    - Clarke, James Freeman, 1810-1888. lecture on John A. Andrews: autograph manuscript, undated., (122); 1 folders
    - Clarke, James Freeman, 1810-1888. Lessons for Sunday school: autograph manuscript, undated., (123); 1 folders
    - Clarke, James Freeman, 1810-1888. M. H. Bagley: autograph manuscript, undated., (124); 1 folders
    - Clarke, James Freeman, 1810-1888. Matthew 4: 4: autograph manuscript sermon, undated., (125); 1 folders
    - Clarke, James Freeman, 1810-1888. Not slothful in business: autograph manuscript sermon, 1848-1857., (126); 1 folders
    - Clarke, James Freeman, 1810-1888. Paper on Western Conference: autograph manuscript, undated., (127); 1 folders
    - Clarke, James Freeman, 1810-1888. Pastoral Committee reports: autograph manuscript, circa 1857-1862., (128); 1 folders
    - Clarke, James Freeman, 1810-1888. Religion for children for Sunday School: autograph manuscript, undated., (129); 1 folders
    - Clarke, James Freeman, 1810-1888. Selection from scriptures: autograph manuscript, various dates., (130); 1 folders
    - Clarke, James Freeman, 1810-1888. Sermons: autograph manuscript, circa 1838-1842., (131); 1 folders
    - Clarke, James Freeman, 1810-1888. Services for Susan Dimock: autograph manuscript, 1874., (132); 1 folders
    - Clarke, James Freeman, 1810-1888. Show I a more excellent way: autograph manuscript sermon, undated., (133); 1 folders
    - Clarke, James Freeman, 1810-1888. Spiritual relationships or The true Church: autograph manuscript, undated., (134); 1 folders
    - Clarke, James Freeman, 1810-1888. The Sunday school: autograph manuscript, undated., (135); 1 folders
    - Clarke, James Freeman, 1810-1888. Tradition: autograph manuscript sermon, 1874., (136); 1 folders
    - Clarke, James Freeman, 1810-1888. Unitarian denomination: autograph manuscript sermon, 1877., (137); 1 folders
    - Clarke, James Freeman, 1810-1888. The Western Unitarian Association: autograph manuscript, 1886., (138); 1 folders
    - Clarke, James Freeman, 1810-1888. Worship in sacred places: autograph manuscript sermon, 1848., (139); 1 folders
    - Clarke, James Freeman, 1810-1888. Why join the church?: autograph manuscript, 1867., (140); 1 folders
- IV. Scrapbooks, journals, sketchbooks, financial records and other papers of James Freeman Clarke
  58M-225. Formerly MS Am 1569.3 (1-26), with some gaps.
  Includes sketches, journals, commonplace book, poems, compositions, prints, clippings, images of James Freeman Clarke, expense books and account books, among other material.
  - Clarke, James Freeman, 1810-1888. Album of European sketches: sketchbook, circa 1849-1853., (141); 1 volume in 1 folder.
    Formerly MS Am 1569.3 (1).
  - Clarke, James Freeman, 1810-1888. Album of European sketches: sketchbook, circa 1849-1853. 1849., (142); 1 volume in 1 folder.
    Formerly MS Am 1569.3 (2).
  - Clarke, James Freeman, 1810-1888. Album of sketches, Rome to Vienna: sketchbook, 1853-1854., (143); 1 volume in 1 folder.
    Formerly MS Am 1569.3 (3).
  - Clarke, James Freeman, 1810-1888. Album of European sketches: sketchbook, circa 1849-1853., (144); 1 volume in 1 folder.
    Formerly MS Am 1569.3 (4).
  - Clarke, James Freeman, 1810-1888. Album of miscellaneous sketches: sketchbook, undated., (145); 1 volume in 1 folder.
    Formerly MS Am 1569.3 (5).
  - Clarke, James Freeman, 1810-1888. New England sketchbook: sketchbook, 1848., (146); 1 volume in 1 folder.
    Formerly MS Am 1569.3 (5a).
  - Clarke, James Freeman, 1810-1888. Commonplace book of poetry: manuscript, printed, undated., (147); 1 volume in 1 folder.
    Formerly MS Am 1569.3 (6).
  - Clarke, James Freeman, 1810-1888. Book of poems: manuscript, 1845-1888., (148); 1 volume in 1 folder.
    Formerly MS Am 1569.3 (7).
  - Clarke, James Freeman, 1810-1888. Poems: manuscript, typescript, printed, undated., (149); 1 volume in 1 folder.
    Formerly MS Am 1569.3 (8).
  - Clarke, James Freeman, 1810-1888. Journal of thoughts and reading: autograph manuscript, 1838., (150); 1 volume in 1 folder.
    Formerly MS Am 1569.3 (9).
  - Clarke, James Freeman, 1810-1888. Journal: autograph manuscript, circa 1838-1844., (151); 1 volume in 1 folder.
    Includes drawings, poems, copied passages, other writings. At back of volume are lists of: Calls and Visits, Letters written, Letters received, Sermons newly written, Messenger.
    Formerly MS Am 1569.3 (10).